Guide to the Jacques Guicharnaud Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jacques Guicharnaud papers
1943-2005
GEN MSS 883
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.88
(27 boxes)
The Jacques Guicharnaud Papers consist of correspondence with literary and teaching colleagues, publishers, family, and friends; autograph manuscript and typescript drafts of plays, literary criticism, and other writings; a small amount of drafts and offprints of literary criticism by colleagues; syllabi, lecture notes, and administrative papers relating to teaching at Yale University and Harvard University; printed material including theater programs and clippings relating to theater in France and the United States; and a small amount of financial records, photographs of colleagues, family, and play productions, and other papers. Most materials date from Guicharnaud's career in the United States; some correspondence and writings from his studies and early career in France are also present. Research strengths include Guicharnaud's writings and teaching career, French theater, and criticism and teaching of French literature in the United States, 1950s-1990s.
Guicharnaud, Jacques, 1924-2005
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the estate of Jacques Guicharnaud on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
Box 24: Restricted until 2045. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Boxes 25-26: Restricted until 2055. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Box 27: Restricted until 2060. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Jacques Guicharnaud (1924-2005)
Jacques Guicharnaud, Benjamin F. Barge Professor Emeritus of French at Yale University, scholar of French theater, and specialist in French literature and drama of the 17th, 18th, and 20th centuries. Guicharnaud was born in Paris, where he was a student during the German occupation in World War II. During the 1940s, he was associated with existentialist philosphers Jean-Paul Sartre, Albert Camus, and Simone de Beauvoir. In 1949, he emigrated to the United States to teach at Bryn Mawr College. Guicharnaud taught at Yale from 1950 to his retirement in 1997, with the exception of an appointment at Harvard University during 1977-1979. At Yale, he was acting master of Jonathan Edwards College, 1968 spring, and Morse College, 1972-1973, and he served on the executive committee of the Yale Theater Studies Program. His writings on French literature include Modern French Theatre From Giraudoux to Beckett, coauthored with June Beckelman (1961) and Molière: une aventure théâtrale: Tartuffe, Don Juan, Le misanthrope (1963). He also wrote and translated plays for theater and television, and coauthored a novel, Santarém, with Yale University history professor Rollin G. Osterweis (1959). He was married to June Beckelman Guicharnaud (1922-1989), an author, editor, and translator.
Scope and Contents
The Jacques Guicharnaud Papers consist of correspondence with literary and teaching colleagues, publishers, family, and friends; autograph manuscript and typescript drafts of plays, literary criticism, and other writings; a small amount of drafts and offprints of literary criticism by colleagues; syllabi, lecture notes, and administrative papers relating to teaching at Yale University and Harvard University; printed material including theater programs and clippings relating to theater in France and the United States; and a small amount of financial records, photographs of colleagues, family, and play productions, and other papers. Most materials date from Guicharnaud's career in the United States; some correspondence and writings from his studies and early career in France are also present. Research strengths include Guicharnaud's writings and teaching career, French theater, and criticism and teaching of French literature in the United States, 1950s-1990s.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Correspondence, circa 1945-circa 2005. II. Writings, 1943-circa 1997. III. Writings by Others, circa 1950-circa 1997. IV. Teaching Materials, circa 1950-circa 1997. V. Printed Material, circa 1950-circa 2005. VI. Other Papers, circa 1950-circa 2005.
Authors, French -- 20th Century -- Archives; College teachers -- United States; Dramatists, French -- 20th Century; Existentialism; French drama -- 17th century -- History and criticism; French drama -- 18th century -- History and criticism; French drama -- 20th Century -- History and criticism; French drama -- Study and teaching -- United States; French literature -- 17th century -- History and criticism; French literature -- 18th century -- History and criticism; French literature -- 20th Century -- History and criticism; French literature -- Study and teaching -- United States; Theater -- France; Theater -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, French; France -- History -- German occupation, 1940-1945; Photographs -- 20th Century; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; College teachers -- United States -- 20th Century; Dramatists -- United States -- 20th Century; Guicharnaud, Jacques, 1924-2005; Guicharnaud, June; Peyre, Henri, 1901-1988; Gallimard (Firm); Harvard University. Department of Romance Languages and Literatures; Jonathan Edwards College (Yale University); Yale School of Drama; Yale University. Dept. of French; Yale University Press
- Correspondence, circa 1945-circa 2005; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Related Archival Materials note
  See also: Teaching Materials
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence includes letters from Henri Peyre, Sterling Professor of French Emeritus at Yale University; other colleagues and students; publishers; and a few letters from early literary associates including Albert Camus, Jean Cocteau, and Jean-Paul Sartre. Correspondence with publishers concerns Guicharnaud's writings, with some accompanying drafts, contracts, and royalty statements. Most letters are incoming, with a small amount of outgoing drafts and typescript carbons.
  - Correspondents, A-B (Box 1)
  - Correspondents, C (Box 1)
  - Correspondents, D (Box 1)
  - Correspondents, E-F (Box 1)
  - Correspondents, G (Box 1)
  - Correspondents, H-L (Box 1)
  - Correspondents, M-N (Box 1)
  - Correspondents, O-P (Box 1)
  - Correspondents, R-S (Box 1)
  - Correspondents, T (Box 1)
  - Correspondents, U-Z (Box 1)
  - Anduze, Berthe (Box 1)
  - Art Institute of Chicago (Box 1)
  - Audiberti, Jacques (Box 1)
  - Barrault, Jean-Louis (Box 1)
  - Béranger, Jean (Box 1)
  - Blum, Antoinette (Box 1)
  - Camus, Albert (Box 1)
  - Camus, Francine Faure (photocopy) (Box 1)
  - Cimura (Box 1)
  - Clément, Alain (Box 1)
  - Cocteau, Jean (Box 1)
  - Coindreau, Maurice Edgar (Box 1)
  - Columbia University Press (Box 1)
  - École normale supérieure (France) (Box 2)
  - Everett Edwards, Inc. (Box 2)
  - Forget, Daniel (Box 2)
  - France, Ambassade (U.S.). Services du conseiller culturel, 3 (Box 2)
  - Gallimard, 4 (Box 2)
  - Ginn and Company, 2 (Box 2)
  - Gorceix, Septime (Box 2)
  - Guicharnaud family (Box 2)
  - Ham, Edward Billings (Box 2)
  - Harper & Row, Publishers (Box 2)
  - Ionesco, Eugène (Box 2)
  - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation (Box 2)
  - Larousse (Box 2)
  - Nobel Committee of the Swedish Academy (Box 2)
  - Northwestern University (Evanston, Ill.) (Box 2)
  - Peyre, Henri (Box 2)
  - Prentice-Hall, Inc., 3 (Box 3)
  - Queneau, Raymond (Box 3)
  - Random House, 4 (Box 3)
  - The Romanic Review (Box 3)
  - Saint-John Perse (Box 3)
    Signed "Alexis Léger"
  - Sartre, Jean-Paul (Box 3)
  - Second Coming Magazine (Box 3)
  - Société des auteurs et compositeurs dramatiques (Box 3)
  - [Tarrencourt-Mouhier?], Marcelle (Box 3)
  - University of Colorado (Box 3)
  - Vaudable, Louis, Madame (Box 3)
  - Yale University Press (Box 3)
  - Unidentified (Box 3)
  - Postage stamps (Box 3)
- Writings, 1943-circa 1997; Series II; 4.17; (11 boxes)
  Organized into three subseries: Notebooks, arranged chronologically, followed by undated; Plays, arranged alphabetically by title; and Other Writings, arranged alphabetically by title, followed by unidentified.
  Most writings are plays, including works by Guicharnaud in French, English translations of his plays, and French translations by Guicharnaud of plays by others. Notebooks contain drafts of plays, unidentified writings, and diary entries dated 1943-1945, 1947-1948, and 1952-1956. Other Writings contain correspondence, publicity materials, and reviews relating to Modern French Theatre From Giraudoux to Beckett, by Guicharnaud and June Beckelman, and Molière: une aventure théâtrale; research materials relating to Santarém, a novel by Guicharnaud and Rollin G. Osterweis; and drafts of essays on literary criticism, book reviews, novels, stories, and poems.
  - Notebooks
    - Notebook, 1943 March-1944 April (Box 4)
    - Notebook, 1944 January-1945 July (Box 4)
    - Notebook, 1944 May-1945 July (Box 4)
      Contains Claudel, Paul, Partage de midi (play). Manuscript copy made by Guicharnaud in 1943
    - Notebook, 1947-1948 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, 1952-1955 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, 1955-1956 (Box 4)
    - Notebook, 1977 June (Box 4)
    - Notebook, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Notebooks, undated; 4 (Box 4)
    - Notebooks, undated; 10 (Box 5)
    - Notebooks, undated; 7 (Box 6)
  - Plays
    - Titles, A-D, circa 1945-circa 1997; 15 (Box 7)
    - Titles, E-Z, circa 1945-circa 1997; 22 (Box 8)
  - Other Writings
    - Modern French Theatre From Giraudoux to Beckett, [circa 1961]; 8 (Box 9)
      By Guicharnaud and June Beckelman
    - Molière: une aventure théâtrale: Tartuffe, Don Juan, Le misanthrope, [circa 1963]; 2 (Box 9)
    - [Molière essays], undated (Box 9)
    - Portrait du Français d'après les romans de Henry James, 1947 (Box 9)
    - Raymond Queneau, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Santarém. Novel, [circa 1959]; 4 (Box 10)
      By Guicharnaud and Rollin G. Osterweis
    - Titles, A-L, circa 1950-circa 1997; 13 (Box 11)
    - Titles, L-Z, circa 1950-circa 1997; 12 (Box 12)
    - Unidentified, circa 1950-circa 1997; 6 (Box 12)
    - Unidentified, circa 1950-circa 1997; 19 (Box 13)
    - Unidentified, circa 1950-circa 1997; 10 (Box 14)
- Writings by Others, circa 1950-circa 1997; Series III; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by author, followed by unidentified.
  Contains drafts, offprints, and photocopies of literary criticism by colleagues.
  - Authors, A-Z, 4 (Box 15)
  - Unidentified, 4 (Box 15)
  - Unidentified, 6 (Box 16)
- Teaching Materials, circa 1950-circa 1997; Series IV; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  See also: Other Papers/Financial papers
  Arranged alphabetically by name of institution, followed by unidentified.
  Materials include syllabi and lectures for courses taught by Guicharnaud, faculty correspondence, and memoranda. Papers relating to Yale University, Jonathan Edwards College, concern budgeting, event programming, and other administrative work by Guicharnaud as acting master during spring, 1968.
  - Harvard University, circa 1977-circa 1979; 7 (Box 17)
  - Yale University, circa 1950-circa 1997; 4 (Box 17)
  - Yale University, circa 1950-circa 1997; 11 (Box 18)
  - Yale University. Jonathan Edwards College, 1967-1968; 5 (Box 18)
  - Unidentified, circa 1950-circa 1997 (Box 18)
- Printed Material, circa 1950-circa 2005; Series V; 1.33; (4 boxes)
  Contains mostly clippings about French and American theater. Unarranged material includes programs from productions of Le Théâtre Français de Yale, the Yale Dramatic Association, and the Yale School of Drama Repertory Theatre.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic, followed by clippings and unarranged material.
  - Americana, 2 (Box 19)
  - Comédie-Française (Box 19)
  - Films, 3 (Box 19)
  - Clippings, 8 (Box 19)
  - Clippings, 12 (Box 20)
  - Clippings, 7 (Box 21)
  - Other printed material, 6 (Box 21)
  - Clippings, 2 (Box 22 (Oversize))
- Other Papers, circa 1950-circa 2005; Series VI; 0.42; (1 box)
  Financial papers concern taxes, insurance and expenses. Some invoices and receipts may relate to Yale University, Jonathan Edwards College. A small amount of photographs consists of images of colleagues, play productions, and unidentified family, possibly including Guicharnaud.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Address books (Box 23)
  - Other addresses (Box 23)
  - Drawings (Box 23)
  - Financial papers, 8 (Box 23)
  - Photographs, 4 (Box 23)
  - Travel, 2 (Box 23)
- Restricted, 1.25; (4 boxes)
  - Restricted papers (Box 24)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted until 2045. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Restricted papers (Box 25)
    Restricted until 2055. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Restricted papers (Box 26)
  - Restricted papers (Box 27)
    Restricted until 2060. For further information consult the appropriate curator.